Welcome to the next
week of our course
on parallel functional
programming with Java.
This week's lessons
pick up where
we left off in our coverage
of parallel stream internals
last week.
We start by delving deeper
into the splitting phase where
a Spliterator is used
to partition a data
source into chunks that are
then processed in parallel
by the applying phase.
Some data sources, such as
the Java ArrayList collection,
split evenly and efficiently,
whereas other data sources,
such as the Java
LinkedList collection,
do not split evenly
and efficiently.
To demonstrate
these differences,
we analyze a program that
quantifies the performance
of parallel Spliterators for
the ArrayList and LinkedList
when processing the complete
works of Shakespeare.
These test results show how
differences in Spliterator
implementations become
more significant
as the size of the
data source grows.
We next turn our attention
to the applying phase
where the chunks created
by a Spliterator run
in the common Java
ForkJoinPool, which
provides a high performance
and fine-grained parallel task
execution engine.
All Java parallel streams
within a process share
a common ForkJoinPool, which
maximizes processor utilization
since this pool controls
how cores are used globally
within the process.
Although the default
number of threads
in the common ForkJoinPool is
one less than the total number
of processor cores known to
the Java execution environment,
a parallel stream can
use all available cores
since the calling thread is
borrowed and used temporarily
as part of the pool.
However, this default
number of threads
may be inadequate
for some programs,
such as I/O bound apps that
download and process content
from the web.
Java therefore enables
programmatic control
of the size of the
common ForkJoinPool
by various means we outline
in this week's lessons.
We also briefly summarize the
structure and functionality
of Java's Fork/Join
framework, which
is covered in much greater
detail later in this course.
The final group of
lessons this week
begin exploring the combining
phase where the Java stream's
framework employs a terminal
operation, such as Collect
or Reduce, to join the
partial results produced
in the common ForkJoinPool
into a final reduced result.
There are subtleties with
programming terminal operations
properly, so we examine
solutions to common traps
and pitfalls of programming
these operations to help
ensure your code is
correct and efficient.