So now that we've finished
covering partitioning
as part of Java
streams internals,
let's turn our attention
to the apply phase.
So remember, partitioning's
part of the split phase.
Now we're going to talk
about the apply phase.
And we're going
to talk about how
to do the parallel processing or
how the parallel processing is
done via the common
ForkJoinPool.
And we'll see that the Java's
parallel streams framework
processes chunks in parallel
using this common ForkJoinPool.
So we've talked briefly about
the common ForkJoinPool.
I'll give you a bit more
discussion of it here.
The real discussion on common
ForkJoinPool and ForkJoinPool
will take place in the
fork/join framework
lessons in subsequent weeks.
But I'm going to give you
a teaser here because it's
important to understand how
all these different pieces work
in order to make sense out
of how the parallel streams
framework behaves.
Real quickly, a ForkJoinPool
provides a high performance,
fine-grained task
execution framework
for Java data parallelism.
And I should also hasten to add
that the Java ForkJoinPool is
an object-oriented framework
rather than a functional
framework.
However, despite the fact
it's not purely functional,
it's actually used extensively
as the parallel computing
engine for many
higher-level frameworks--
parallel streams,
CompletableFutures, as well as
other frameworks that you
might find in other languages
that are based on Java and
the Java virtual machine.
The ForkJoinPool
itself is a class
that implements the
ExecutorService interface
indirectly.
If you take a look at
this class hierarchy,
you can see that the
ExecutorService is an interface
that implements Executor.
And then there's a
Java Class, which
is an abstract class called the
AbstractExecutorService that
implements ExecutorService
and provides
a bunch of implementations
of common methods
that are shared by various
concrete classes that
extend AbstractExecutorService.
ThreadPoolExecutor is
one class that extends
the AbstractExecutorService.
ThreadPoolExecutor's covered
in detail in my other course
on concurrent
object-oriented programming,
as is
ScheduledThreadPoolExecutor.
But now we're going to focus
on ForkJoinPool, which,
as you can see, extends
AbstractExecutorService, which
implements ExecutorService.
So a ForkJoinPool
can do many things.
It can obviously
do things that you
get with the
ExecutorService interface.
But its real purpose in life is
to execute so-called fork/join
tasks.
And a fork/join task
is another class
that associates a chunk of
data along with a computation
on that data in order to enable
this fine-grained parallelism
that's so important in
modern multiprocessor,
multicore systems.
A fork/join task is
something like a Java thread,
but it's much lighter weight.
In particular,
the fork/join task
does not have its
own run-time stack,
does not have its own registers.
It does not have its own
thread-local storage.
It doesn't have all
the other mechanisms
that a regular Java thread has
down into the operating system
kernel, and so on.
One of the nice things about
the fact it's lighter weight
is you can actually have a
very large number of fork/join
tasks, thousands, or
tens of thousands,
or hundreds of
thousands, depending
on how big your computer is,
that can then be multiplexed
and run atop a much smaller
number of Java worker
threads in a ForkJoinPool.
And in this case,
the worker thread
would, in fact,
be a Java thread.
And typically as
we'll see, by default
the number of threads in a
fork/join worker thread pool
are roughly around the
number of processor cores
that the Java execution
environment knows about.
So you can basically
think of parallel streams
as being a user friendly
functional programming
facade for the object-oriented
ForkJoinPool class
and the fork/join framework.
And so rather than having
to do all the mechanisms
we're going to talk
about later when
we go into detail about how the
ForkJoinPool framework behaves,
parallel streams
just wrap things up
with this nice functional
veneer with the streams
and the composition and
all the other good things.
Of course, it's always
possible to choose to program
to the ForkJoinPool API
directly if you so choose.
But it can be somewhat painful.
Of course, we will
go through this.
And you will learn how to do it,
because there's some times when
you need to do it.
And we'll talk
about why you might
need to do it in a minute.
But just be aware that
it's a bit more painful.
I'm a big Lord of the Rings fan.
So I took the
liberty of lampooning
one of the famous scenes
of The Lord of the Rings
where Saruman tells Gandalf,
I gave you the chance
of programming Java streams.
But you have elected
the way of pain
and programmed with
the ForkJoinPool.
If you'd like to see how to
program with the ForkJoinPool,
there's some interesting
examples in the fork--
in the Search with Fork/Join
class in the SearchStreamGang
framework case study.
And this uses the
common ForkJoinPool
to search input strings
for phrases that match.
It's more interesting
and complicated
than some of the other stuff,
but it's cool to look at.
The main reason you would
ever use the ForkJoinPool
directly is if the
programming model
that you are trying to
implement doesn't really
match well with what
parallel streams provides.
And the parallel stream model
is this very rigid divide
and conquer style approach.
And if your tasks don't
quite fit with that,
maybe you're better off using
the ForkJoinPool directly.
So here's an example
that you could actually
find on the web that
counts the occurrence
of a word in document folders.
And here's just a little
snippet of that code.
This is the compute
method from that example.
This is showing
the ForkJoinPool.
And what we do
here is we go ahead
and we create a LinkedList
of recursive tasks.
I'll talk more about what
recursive tasks are later.
But we have this LinkedList
of recursive tasks.
And then we go ahead and we go
through all the subdirectories
in a given folder.
And for each of these
subdirectories in a given
folder, we go ahead
and create a new object
that will search for
the word in that folder.
And we create this as a
so-called FolderSearchTask,
which is a recursive task.
And then we go ahead and add
that task to our forks list.
And then we fork it.
So that goes out
and says, arrange
to run this task in one
of the worker threads
in the ForkJoinPool thread pull.
And then we go through the
documents in a given folder.
And we make a
document search task,
which will search for the
word in that document.
And then we go ahead and
add that task to our forks
list and fork that task,
which again arranges
to have this task
running in some worker
thread in the ForkJoinPool.
So all those things will
now be forked and off
and running and doing their
thing and whatever they
need to do to do the searching.
And then the last
thing we do here
is we go through a loop that's
going to essentially iterate
through the forks list and
join each of those tasks
and join basically blocks until
the task has got its result.
It logically blocks for
reasons we'll talk about later.
It actually pitches
in to do some
of the processing using
the thread of the caller
to do some work.
And when that task is complete,
when the fork is finished
with its compute,
then we get the number
of counts of the word back and
increment the count variable.
And when the loop is finished,
all of the background tasks
have finished, and
we get the count back
from the whole operation.
So that's the final
count that we get here.
Now again, I think
you'll probably
agree that this code
doesn't look anything
like parallel streams.
It looks like
object-oriented programming.
And it doesn't look
like the classic divide
and conquer style approach.
It's more about
recursive decomposition.
And so as a result, it's
a little more complicated
to program.
But it very well may run
faster than trying to use
parallel streams for this.
And later on when we talk
about the ForkJoinPool,
I'll show you some
examples that compare
and contrast different
styles of programming
with the fork/join
framework as well as
comparing and contrasting how
to program the same code using
parallel streams.
And this will really
give us a good chance
to do an apples-to-apples
comparison of the performance
results.
All parallel streams
in a process share
the same common ForkJoinPool.
There could only be
one of these things.
And the reason for this is
to help optimize resource
utilization by allowing
that common ForkJoinPool
to know what cores are
actually being used globally
within a process.
So you can think
of it like Cerebro
from the X-Men where Professor
X can get a global view of all
the things that are taking
place within his mind's purview.
And so this allows better
resource utilization.
This type of global versus local
resource management trade-off
is very common in
other computing
examples, other
computing usages,
as well as other domains.
So for example, if you take
a look at the Java free store
management with
the Java Heap where
you try to have a global
heap to manage memory,
which can be garbage
collected, rather
than having a bunch of
private heaps or private lists
to manage pools of
data independently
of one global heap.
That's another good example of
going for this global resource
management approach versus
a local resource management
approach.
And there's lots of other
examples too, some of which
are described in the link at
the bottom of the page, which
talks about business models.
Ironically, there
are very few knobs
to control the common
ForkJoinPool, or really
any ForkJoinPool
for that matter.
They're really all done
in very much one size fits
all like approach.
And the simplicity
is intentional.
If you watch this excellent
video by my good friend
and colleague, Doug
Lea, who actually
wrote the bulk of the
java.util.concurrent package
and also wrote the bulk
of the ForkJoinPool
and a lot of the stream stuff
and various synchronizers
and so on, you'll find that they
designed this for a purpose.
And the whole idea was
to let the framework do
the heavy lifting rather than
providing all kinds of knobs
that would confuse developers
and often make things worse,
quite frankly.
We should contrast the
simplicity of ForkJoinPool
with the elaborate API
nature of ThreadPoolExecutor,
which has lots and
lots and lots of knobs
that can be turned
and controlled
in all kinds of ways.
If you take my concurrent
object-oriented programming
class, you should watch the
video on ThreadPoolExecutor
carefully and learn about
all the different policies
and so on that can
be set to use this.
One thing that can be
configured, however,
with the ForkJoinPool
is its size.
And there's a couple of
different ways to do this.
I won't really talk
about them at the moment.
We're going to talk about
them more in the next upcoming
lesson.
But basically you can either
set the number of threads
globally once before the
program really starts to run,
or you can use something
called a managed blocker, which
is a more dynamic way
of setting these values.