So now that we've
talked about how
to configure the common
fork-join pool, let's go ahead
and demonstrate how you can
configure this pool in practice
and see what some
of the benefits
are of actually doing
that configuration.
So in this particular
case, we're
going to run several different
examples to illustrate
how you can either not
or you can configure
the size of the
common fork-join pool,
and then we'll see the
implications on performance
as a result of those
various configurations.
This example is available in
my EX 20 folder in my GitHub
repository, so I
strongly recommend
you take a look at
that and follow along.
So as we mentioned before,
the common fork-join pool size
can in fact be controlled
programmatically.
This particular demo
applies managed blocker
in a couple of different ways
to add new worker threads
to the common fork-join
pool, and you'll
see that there's a
bunch of different ways
in which this works.
One way is the
rather verbose way
of doing it that
I show you here.
There's a cooler way of doing
it using a little helper
class called a blocking
task, and we'll
talk about both of those
when we walk through the code
here in just a minute.
The behavior of this program
is measured and quantified
using a function that's
called test download behavior.
And this function demonstrates
the performance differences
of using managed blocker
versus not using the managed
blocker for an
I/O intensive app,
basically an app that
downloads images from websites.
As you can see here, this
test download behavior method
is passed a parameter
that's a function,
and this function
maps URLs to files.
And we use this thing to
pass in different strategies
for downloading and storing
images from remote websites.
And so this is basically the
good old strategy pattern
from the Gang of Four
book, and we'll take a look
at three strategies.
We'll take a look
at one strategy
that just download and stores
as images without using any
managed blocker
mechanisms whatsoever,
so it'll be limited to
the number of threads
and the default coming
fork-join pool size.
And then we'll also
show a strategy
that downloads and stores
images using a managed
blocker directly, and
then finally we'll
show an example that uses
the manage blocker wrapped up
in a helper class
called a blocking task,
which is really cool
and very reusable.
When we run the demo--
I'll show this to you as we do
it, but here's a little preview
of coming attractions.
The results show that increasing
the number of worker threads
via the manage blocker
mechanism, of course,
improves the performance.
So this particular example is
going to download and store
42 images from my website.
And as you can
see, when we do it
with 12 threads, which is
the default number of threads
on my six core
hyper-threaded laptop,
you'll see that the performance
of that is slower than the
Other approaches that use either
the managed blocker directly
or the blocking task wrapper.
And so this just demonstrates
you do get a benefit.
Now, of course, your
mileage will always vary,
but I think it
demonstrates conclusively
that adding threads
can make a difference.
And the manage blocker mechanism
can make things run faster.
So let's go ahead now and
take a look at the source code
and I'll run the example and
we'll see how it all works.
We're now going to walk through
an example that illustrates how
to combine the Java
parallel streams framework
with and without the
fork-join managed blocker
interface in order
to demonstrate
the impact of
having more threads
in the common fork-join
pool on overall performance.
This test actually
takes a while to run,
so I'm going to
go ahead and start
running this in the background.
By the time we're done,
we should hopefully
get the results back,
and we can present them.
So here's the EX 20 class.
As you can see,
all it does is it
goes ahead and creates
an instance of itself
and runs the test.
This starts out by printing the
number of available processors
that the Java execution
environment thinks it has.
In my case, as you'll see,
if you peek back over here,
we end up starting
out with 12 cores
because this is running
on a six-core machine.
Come back to that later.
We warm up the
thread pool to make
sure everything's ready
to go, and then we
run three different tests
or three different versions
of the same test.
There's a run test method
we'll look at in a second,
and we pass different
functions into this.
The first one will just
download and store images
using the default behavior of
Java's fork-join framework,
which does not add new
worker threads to the pool.
Then we'll store-- use a
different implementation that
will download and store images
using the managed blocker
mechanism directly, which
does add new worker threads
to the pool adaptively
and dynamically
when blocking occurs.
And finally we'll run the test
passing in download and store
image BT, which is
the blocking task
wrapper for the manage
blocker mechanism.
So that's the big picture view.
And, of course,
each time we pass
in which test version is running
so we can see what happens.
Here's the Run Test method.
It takes this function as
input in the name of the test.
First thing it does is
run the garbage collector
to give more accurate timings.
And then we go ahead and run
the test download behavior
function, which is
a helper function,
passing in the download
and store image
function and the test name.
And this is just so we can
consolidate all the timing
in one place.
Here is download-- here's
test download behavior.
This is really the heavy
worker for all these things.
As you can see, it
takes this function
to download and
store images, which
could be one of any three
different implementations.
And what we do as we go ahead
and we get a list of URLs,
and those URLs are actually
links to my website.
We then convert those URLs
into a parallel stream.
We call map passing in the
appropriate function that
was passed in to download
and store the image.
And then we go ahead
and terminate the stream
and collect the results
into a list of images.
So far so good.
And when we're all done,
we print out the statistics
for this particular test run.
Here is the based default
version of download and store
image.
This downloads and stores
an image from a year
URL without using the adaptive
mechanisms in the Java
fork-join's pool frameworks
managed blocker mechanism.
So this will not expand
the pool of worker threads,
and all we do is we simply
download the image and store
it.
And we'll take a look at
download images later,
but it just downloads the image.
Here is the download and
store image MB version.
This uses the fork-join
frameworks manage
blocker mechanism explicitly.
And I had to do a
little sleazy trick
to make this work
because of the fact
that this is not really
lambda expressions
and cool Java 8 stuff.
This is Java 7 stuff, so
what we have to do here
is we have to go
ahead and create
ourselves an anonymous inner
class of an instance of managed
blocker.
That class we'll
look at the second.
That will be passed
to the managed block
method, which is a static method
defined on fork-join pool.
And the key method here that
matters is the block method.
And you can see that
one block is called,
it will turn around
and download the image,
store the result into
a one element array.
This is a sleazy trick here,
but it works for our purposes.
And we get the image download.
This will block,
but this will also
cause the fork-join pool--
the common fork-join pool
to expand the number of
threads whenever we block.
And when we're done, we go ahead
and store the image and return.
The third and final
implementation
is download and store image BT.
This is a lot more
concise because we
use the blocking task call
and manage block method.
We'll talk more about this
method in later sessions.
We'll talk about it
when we talk about how
to configure the fork-join
pool's common thread
pool in our later
lessons in the course.
But for right now,
this basically
encapsulates all this
wacky anonymous innerclass
gobbledygook and gives us a
nice clean method to call,
and we pass in a lambda
supplier, which in this case
downloads the image.
And under the hood the call
and manage block method
does the manage
blocker mechanism
and then stores the image.
Here's the image--
here's the method that
actually downloads an image.
As you can see, it just takes
the URL, downloads the content,
and creates a new image for it.
So that's basically the program.
We print out some statistics
and do some other stuff.
But that's the real logic.
Now that we've gone
through the code,
let's quickly go over here
and look at the behavior.
As you can see, we had 12
cores, and the test download--
sorry, test default
download behavior method
downloaded and stored 42 images
using 12 threads in the pool.
That's all we had.
The test adaptive and
the download behavior
downloaded and stored 42
images using 43 threads,
and that's the same behavior
we have with the adaptive BT
download behavior.
And here then are the
performance results.
As you might expect, the one
that doesn't expand the thread
pool takes the longest
time to download,
and the ones that do expand
the thread pool take less time.
And I think it's
kind of interesting
that the little wrapper
code that I used actually
performs the best.
That one performs very well.
Maybe it's just because
the cache is fresher,
but the bottom
line is increasing
the number of
threads in the pool
is correlated with
increased performance.