What we're going
to do now is we're
going to actually
demonstrate the performance
of a spliterator so you
can see the differences
between different
types of collections.
In particular, I'm going
to show the performance
impact of different
Java collections
on the performance
of their spliterators
as they're applied
in parallel streams.
So before I actually walk
through the code, which,
by the way, is in this ex14
folder in my GitHub repository,
I'll first give you a
little overview of what
we're going to be seeing.
So as we saw in our previous
discussion, spliterators
for ArrayList and spliterators
for LinkedList partition data
quite differently.
So it's apples to
oranges, if you will.
As we just saw, the trySplit
method for ArrayList
splits very evenly
and very efficiently.
It doesn't copy any data.
It does no unnecessary work.
Whereas in contrast,
LinkedList's spliterator
doesn't split evenly,
doesn't split efficiently,
and has to copy a bunch of data.
So it just doesn't give
you the same benefits
that the ArrayList does.
I wrote a program that
times the differences
of these different spliterators
for ArrayList and LinkedList
when used with parallel
streams and when
applied to process the
complete works of Shakespeare.
And so the actual
method is called
timeParallelStreamUppercase.
We'll look at this method
in more detail in a moment.
And basically it's
passed a list of words,
which could either
be an ArrayList
or could be a LinkedList.
And it's also
passed the test name
so we can indicate
what test was wrong.
And then what we do here is we
repeatedly split and uppercase
the word list using a
parallel spliterator.
So I'll talk through this more
when we look at the actual code
here in a second.
But basically we're just
doing a bunch of busy work
and seeing the effect that
a different spliterator has
on the overall performance
of the program.
Here is just a synopsis
of the results.
And I'll go through
them briefly here.
And then we can
talk more about them
when we run the
program in a minute.
These results demonstrate
that as the size of the input
grows, as we have larger
and larger amounts of words
to split and to
process, the differences
between the ArrayList
and the LinkedList become
more pronounced.
So when we only have
a thousand words
from the works of Shakespeare,
LinkedList and ArrayList
perform about the same.
As we have 10,000 words, they
still perform about the same.
As we get 100,000
words, all of a sudden,
LinkedList is getting
slower than ArrayList.
And when we have
the complete works
of Shakespeare words, which
is something like 883,000,
then all of a sudden, ArrayList
is much faster than LinkedList.
And the reason for
that is just the way
in which LinkedList's
spliterator
doesn't split evenly and
doesn't split efficiently.
And we'll talk more
about this when
we talk about other
aspects of when
not to use parallel
streams in upcoming weeks.
So here we actually
have the program.
And it's in the ex14 folder.
And I'm going to
go ahead and walk
through the code at this point
and show you how it works
and why it works
the way it does.
Now that I've given you an
overview of the test that
evaluates the performance
of different spliterators
for different types of
collections, let's go ahead
and look at the code.
Before we look at the code, I'll
just start running the test.
And this will go ahead and
execute in the background.
We'll close this down.
I'll look at the code.
By the time we're done, the
test should be finished.
So this is the ex14 program.
And it illustrates a
bunch of different things.
In particular,
it's going to show
the difference in performance
by using parallel spliterators
to split a Java LinkedList
versus a Java ArrayList
into chunks.
As you can see, we're going
to run a number of iterations
of the test.
We're going to give it the
complete works of Shakespeare
as the input file.
And there's a number of other
tests here, some of which
we'll look at later.
But right now, we're
just going to focus
on runSpliteratorTests.
So we can go over here and
find runSpliteratorTests.
Here's runSpliteratorTests.
As you can see, what
we do is we start out
by making an ArrayList
of test sizes.
So we have 1,000, 10,000,
100,000, and up to a million.
We won't actually
do the million,
because there are
not a million words
in the works of Shakespeare.
Down here we have
a forEach loop.
So for each time through one of
these test numbers, we come in
and we open up the complete
works of Shakespeare,
getting the limit in as how
many words we want for this run.
As you can see, we start out
with an ArrayList of words,
because that's what gets
returned by getInput.
We then turn around and
convert that ArrayList
into a LinkedList.
So now we have an ArrayList
version and a LinkedList
version.
Then we start the tests.
And the tests are
basically going
to run this function called
timeParallelStreamUppercase,
passing it in the arrayWords and
passing it in the LinkedWords.
So now that we've done that,
we can go ahead and search down
to find
timeParallelStreamUppercase.
As you can see,
this method takes
the name of the test
and a list, which
will either be the
ArrayList or it'll
be the list of linkedWords.
Down in here we come and we
have a really cool little helper
program, helper
function, called timeRun
that will time all these runs.
We run this particular test.
We create an ArrayList
just to store the results.
And then for the number
of iterations in the test,
we're going to go ahead
and turn the words
list into a parallelStream,
which, of course, will either
use the ArrayList's
spliterator or the LinkedList's
spliterator.
And once we have a
stream, we're going
to go ahead and convert each
of the elements in the stream
from a character sequence to a
string and then uppercase it.
And that's just to do
something interesting to make
that could take some time.
And then we go ahead and
convert that into a list
and store it at the
end of this ArrayList.
And we just do that
multiple times.
So that's how the test works.
Let's now go and see--
I'm pretty sure by this
point that the test
is finished running.
And you can see for the
spliterator versions, which
is up here a little
bit earlier, you
can see that for a spliterator
test for a thousand words,
they basically ran identically.
It didn't take very
long to run at all.
For 10,000 words, we can see
that the ArrayList pulls ahead.
It's a little faster.
In fact, the funny part is,
for just a thousand words,
LinkedList actually ran faster,
which is a little surprising.
But then as we get
larger amounts of words,
as we have 100,000
words, ArrayList
is definitely pulling ahead.
And by the time we get up to the
number of words in Shakespeare,
which is as you can see
here, 883,311, at this point
the ArrayList version
is way faster.
So that's just illustrating
how we get a better
result for using parallel
streams with ArrayLists
because they split evenly,
they split efficiently,
they don't copy data,
than for LinkedList,
which doesn't split evenly,
doesn't split efficiently,
and does copy data.