We'll continue our coverage of
Java Parallel Streams Internals
by turning our attention to
partitioning, which, of course,
is part of the splitting phase.
In this discussion,
I'll explain how
Java parallel streams partitions
a data source into chunks.
If you recall our
earlier discussion when
we were talking about
sequential streams,
I mentioned the concept
of a splitable iterator,
or spliterator,
which we'll now talk
about applying to partition
the Java parallel stream
into chunks.
Earlier, we showed
how the spliterator
could be used to traverse
elements in the source.
For example, if you
go back and watch
the Overview of Spliterators
lesson from previous weeks,
you'll see how we
used a spliterator
to take a quote, which
was a list of strings,
convert that quote
into a spliterator
by using the spliterator
factory method--
which is part of the
list interface, which
it inherits from collection--
and then we can use
the tryAdvance method
on the spliterator to
traverse through every element
in that list and do something
with it, like print it out,
for example.
What we're now
going to do is we're
going to talk about how a
parallel spliterator can
be used to partition all
the elements in a source.
So this is different
from traversing.
This is about splitting things
up and breaking things up.
The way this works is by
using the trySplit method
on the spliterator.
And this method--
the trySplit method--
is conventionally called
by the streams framework,
not by a user application.
Of course, you could write
an application to do this,
but it would be very
uncharacteristic and unusual.
So trySplit is what
the streams framework
uses to recursively partition
a data source up into chunks.
In this particular
case, we use a list,
but of course, it could be other
types of collections as well.
The way to implement tri
split most effectively
is to split the input
evenly, as long as it's not
less than some minimum size.
Obviously, if you're trying
to split up an array list,
you don't want to split
anything once you've
got an element with just
one single value in it.
You can't split now an
array element of size 1
into anything more fine-grain.
That's the atomic range of
an element in an array list.
So if you're not
the minimum size,
if you're greater
than the minimum size,
then you try to split the
input up into two chunks--
ideally, even-sized chunks.
And then, as we'll
see, you will want
to return a spliterator
for the left chunk
and update the object itself
to hold the right chunk.
Spliterators very rarely, if
ever, need any synchronization,
nor does it even
need a join phase.
Synchronization is not
needed because splitting
is done in one thread,
not multiple threads.
And there's no need
for a join phase
because joining is done by later
parts of the streams framework,
in particular, typically
by some kind of collector
in the combine phase.
TrySplit is called
recursively until the chunks
are less than or
equal to whatever
the designated minimum size is.
When the size is less than
or equal to minimum size,
then a spliterator is
obliged to return null.
When a null is
returned, that indicates
that we've reached
the minimum size,
and that's an indication
to the framework
that it should do
something else.
In particular, what typically
happens when a trySplit
method returns null, that's a
sign to the streams framework
to process the chunk that you've
got sequentially at that point,
typically by calling its
tryAdvance method on it.
So trySplit is basically
used to break things up
until you get to
minimum sized chunks,
and then streams framework
turns control over
to the tryAdvance method.
Let's take a look
at a Java collection
that splits evenly
and efficiently,
and that's the
ArrayList collection.
If you take a look at the
link the bottom of the slide,
it's actually the source code
for the Java 8 ArrayList class.
And we're going to
zoom in on two methods
here, the trySplit method
and the tryAdvance method.
And as you can see here
by my use of an icon that
indicates a balance scale,
this particular collection
splits evenly.
So trySplit is what does
the heavy lifting here.
As you can see,
what trySplit does
is it goes ahead and
computes the current index
and it computes the high range,
which is called getFence.
Think of that as the end of
the region, end of the range,
or 1 past the end of the range.
And then it goes ahead and
it adds the current index
to the high value
and right shifts
by 1, which is the
same as dividing by 2.
Not sure why they
don't divide by 2.
I'm sure modern Java compiler
can optimize division
by 2 quite nicely.
So that ends up
with the midpoint.
And you can see here,
if low is greater
than or equal to the mid,
that means we're done.
We've reached the end of
this recursive decomposition,
in which case, we
just return null.
Otherwise, we create a
new ArrayList spliterator,
passing in the list,
passing in the low value,
and then passing
in the mid value.
So that's going to
become the new range
for the left-hand
side of the split.
So that will be low to mid.
And you'll also notice that
we set index to be mid.
So that updates this
spliterator so it
will now only have the right
hand portion from mid to high.
So that's how the trySplit
method works for ArrayList.
As you can see, it splits
evenly and there's nothing left
to split-- until there's
nothing left to split,
and it doesn't do any copying.
Here's the tryAdvance method.
This consumes a single
element on each call.
And as you can see here, if
we haven't reached the end,
we go ahead and we
accept the element data
at index i in the list.
So that basically goes ahead
and just kind of copies
by reference the contents
of the list at that element,
and then returns
that as the quote,
"out parameter," if you will,
to the tryAdvance method,
which then returns true if
we successfully got an item.
Otherwise, it returns false,
meaning that we're done.
So that's how ArrayList works.
And I think you'll agree
that it's very efficient,
and it's also going
to be extremely even--
splits everything up
in a nice, even way.
In contrast, other
Java collections
don't split evenly
and efficiently.
The best example that
I'm showing here--
because it's a sibling to
ArrayList is LinkedList.
So as you see, again,
with the unbalanced scale,
this does not split
evenly, and it turns out
it doesn't split
efficiently either.
So here's what trySplit does.
TrySplit splits the
list up into batches
rather than attempting
to split it evenly.
And in fact, if you take a
close look at the code here,
it's quite muddled
and complicated,
but what it's
basically doing is it's
copying a chunk of the list into
an array, which is a batch unit
size, and it then
goes ahead and copies
the contents of the
list into that array,
and then calls a spliterator
helper method to create
a spliterator for that.
And this will have to
take place multiple times
as it moves through the list.
So this is not going
to split evenly,
and it's also not going to split
efficiently because we have
to iterate and we have to copy.
Here's the tryAdvance method.
This actually isn't too slow.
It basically does
some sanity checking,
and then goes ahead and accepts
the current element in the list
into the action that's passed
as a consumer parameter,
and then goes ahead and
updates the current element
to point to the next
element in the list.
So this, again, returns
true if we're successfully
able to advance
and get an element.
Otherwise, it returns
false if we're done.
So I think you'll agree
that LinkedList does not
split evenly, does
not split efficiently
relative to ArrayList.
And that will make
a big difference
for parallel
streams performance,
as we will see somewhat later.
We're going to talk
about more implementation
details for parallel
spliterator in upcoming lessons.
In particular, there's
a lesson on the search
with parallel
spliterator example
and the trySplit method
that is embodied in that.
And I think you'll see that
you can do really cool things
if you have the need to make
super optimized parallel
spliterator using trySplit
for complex data structures.