We're now going to focus on the
second half of our discussion
of combining results.
In the previous
part of the lesson,
I described the differences
between collect and reduce
with respect to
combining partial results
into a single result
in the context
of non-concurrent collectors.
What we're going
to do now is talk
about some of the common
traps and pitfalls
of doing these types of
things with parallel streams.
The key point of this is to
realize that collect and reduce
are different in
terms of what they
expect in the context
of a parallel stream.
Understanding these
semantic differences
is particularly
important if you start
writing complex code
and attempt to use
the reduce terminal operation.
As a consequence, it's
usually a good idea
if you use reduce to
test your solution
with a parallel stream,
even if you're not
planning to use a
parallel stream,
in order to detect
mistakes with respect
to differences between mutable
and immutable reductions.
So this example here, which
is from my ex17 folder
on my GitHub repository,
illustrates the point
quite nicely.
This example is called
buggyStreamReduce3.
And you'll see how it
works and how it goes awry.
What we do is we go ahead
and take a list of words.
These could be all the words
of Shakespeare, for example.
And we store these
things into a stream.
Now, notice that this particular
call, allWords.stream,
doesn't do anything
because streams are lazy.
And so nothing's going to happen
until the terminal operation is
reached a few lines
down in the code.
We then do some clever
conditional checking.
And if the parallel Boolean
flag is set to true,
we will enable parallelism
for this stream.
Conversely if the parallelism--
the parallel flag is false,
we will not enable parallelism.
It turns out that you can
actually have multiple calls
to parallelism--
to parallel or
sequential like this.
And whichever one
occurs last is the one
that dictates the behavior and
the semantics of the stream.
It would be rather odd
to keep changing them.
But I guess it's possible.
So you just have to
be aware of the fact
that the last one called
is the one that wins.
When this code is called
with parallel set to false,
everything is fine,
because the StringBuilder
that we're going to be using
here as the initial seed
value for reduce works fine
when called in a single thread.
However, if we turn
parallel to true,
then chaos and
insanity will result
since reduce expects to be
doing an immutable reduction.
And what we're doing
here unfortunately
is we're passing
in a StringBuilder.
And StringBuilder, as
you may or may not know,
is actually not a
thread-safe class.
So if you create
a StringBuilder,
it's expected to only be
called in a single thread
or called with some other
external lock held to protect
access to the StringBuilder.
And that's because it's got
shared mutable state inside it.
Well, reduce is not
expecting its objects
to have shared mutable state.
It's expecting them
to be immutable.
So if we use this
particular code here,
bad things will happen, because
when different threads that
are running in the parallel
stream's thread pool
try to append into
the StringBuilder,
they will end up corrupting
the state of the StringBuilder.
And really bad
things will occur.
So this is a good
example of code
that succeeds
accidentally when it
works with a sequential stream
but fails horribly when you
run it with a parallel stream.
There are a number of different
ways you could fix this.
One way to fix this is
shown in this example
called streamReduceConcat, which
is also from my ex17 folder.
And this uses reduce with
built-in string concatenation.
So you can see what we
do here is we go ahead
and create a new string,
which, by its very nature,
is immutable.
Strings are immutable in Java.
And then when we go ahead
and do the actual accumulator
operation there,
we take one string.
And we add it to another string
using the plus sign, which
is string concatenation.
This approach will
work correctly,
because it obeys the
semantics that reduce expects
with respect to immutability
of its operations.
However, it's going to be very
inefficient, because you have
to do string concatenation.
And that ends up
making lots of copies.
Yet another way
to do this, which
is arguably the
best way to do it,
is to get rid of
using reduce at all.
And this example is shown
in streamCollectJoining.
And you'll see why it's
called streamCollectJoining
in a second, because we
replaced the use of reduce
with collect along with the
so-called joining collector.
And what happens here
is we collect things
and we use the joining collector
and the joining method call,
which is part of the collector's
utility class in the Java
streams framework.
We'll go ahead and
create a collector that
will correctly and
efficiently join together
the elements in
a parallel stream
by using a
non-concurrent collector.
So it turns out this is
actually a much better solution
than trying to use
reduce with strings
or obviously using reduce
with string builders, which
is a disaster.
So this is a disaster.
This is going to work, but
we'll have more overhead
than we want.
This approach is really
the best way to go.
So the point here
is you just have
to be careful with using
collect and reduce.
You also have to be
careful with respect
to issues related to
associativity and identity
with reduce.
And these examples
are once again
shown by a couple of test
programs in the ex17 example
folder.
The first example
illustrates the fact
that you can only use reduce
on associative operations
for parallel streams.
This code would
work fine if we were
doing addition,
which is associative,
or multiplication,
which is associative.
But if we try to use it in
parallel for subtraction,
it will fail because
subtraction is not associative.
So it'll end up getting
very strange results.
There's another subtle issue
having to do with identity.
And the code that we
see here will work fine
as long as the identity
parameter is going to be 0.
And that's, of course,
because 0 is the identity
operation of addition.
Identity of an
operation, like addition,
is defined as the
identity value given
the operation and some
value will yield the value.
So obviously, 0 plus some
number yields the number.
Or some number plus
0 yields the number.
So if you give a value
here that's not 0,
this code will fail.
Here's another example
where we're showing
identity for multiplication.
In this particular case,
we have to make sure
that the identity value
is 1, because, of course,
the identity of
multiplication is 1.
1 times any number
yields that number.
Any number times 1
If you try to pass in a 0 here
as the identity value-- which
works fine for,
well, for addition--
it'll obviously fail horribly,
because 0 times any number
equals 0.
So these are rather
subtle points.
But it's important to understand
the limitations of reduce.
If you'd like more
discussion about this,
there's an excellent
online tutorial
you can find by my friend and
colleague, Angelika Langer.
And she talks about
reduce versus collect
and goes into lots
more detail about
many other interesting
aspects of these two terminal
operations.
So I recommend you take
a look at that video
if you have some time.