Now that we've wrapped
up our discussion
of Java parallel stream
internals related
to the applying phase,
let's turn our attention
to the Java parallel
stream internals
for the combining phase,
starting with the discussion
of combining results.
In this part of the lesson, I'll
talk about how a reduction can
be performed to combine partial
results into a single result.
After the common fork-join
pool finishes processing
the chunks, their
partial results
are combined into a final
so-called reduced result.
This discussion
here assumes we're
talking about
non-concurrent collectors.
We'll talk about concurrent
collectors later.
As you can see in the
diagram, partial results
occur at multiple phases
while the reductions
are taking place, culminating
in a single join that brings
everything together at the end.
The joins always occur in a
single thread at each level,
typically in the parent
of the child tasks.
And so you can see here
that the children will then
be used by the parent to
join the results together
into a merged result.
Because it's always
performed in a single thread,
there's really no need
to have synchronizers
at all during the joining.
The only reason you'd
ever do synchronization
is if there was something else
you were synchronizing with,
but you don't have to worry
about synchronizing the results
from the pool that's
coming out with the results
from being processed
in the applying phase.
Different terminal operations
combine partial results
in different ways.
It's particularly important to
understand these differences
for parallel streams, which
we'll be talking about later.
Reduce creates a
new, immutable value.
Here's an example.
This is our factorial
example, where
we're going to generate a stream
of longs from, in this case,
let's say, 1 to 8 in parallel.
And then we're going to
go ahead and reduce them.
I've visualized this at the
top of the right-hand portion
of the slide.
So you can see that we have
a range of longs from 1 to 8,
and the parallel spliterator
will then go ahead
and split that up into chunks,
say, first range 1 to 4,
and then 5 to 8, and then that
will be further decomposed
by the parallel spliterator
into, say, the range is 1 to 2,
3 to 4, 5 to 6, and 7 and 8.
So that's how things are
going to be decomposed.
This example is also available
in my ex16 folder in my GitHub
repository.
At this point,
the reductions can
occur, and keep in mind our
point of all this discussion
is to show that reduce
creates immutable results.
So what's going
to happen here is
we're going to end up
pairwise multiplying
the values together.
So obviously, 1 times 2 is 2, 3
times 4 is 12, 5 times 6 is 30,
and seven times 8 is 56.
But then those reductions are
done up the reduction tree.
So the next reductions
will be multiplying 2
by 12, which will reduce
to 24, and 30 by 56,
which reduces to 1680.
And then, finally, we'll
end up multiplying 24
by 1680 to produce the
final reduced result, which
is 40,320.
And the key thing I
want you to realize here
is that reduces combining
two immutable values--
in this case, a long--
and produces a new value.
We don't ever change the
values once they're created.
We simply use them for further
stages in the reduction
until we reach the final result.
In contrast, collect mutates
an existing results container.
So it changes the
results container
rather than assuming
that it's immutable.
Here's another example
to illustrate this point.
We're not going to be able to
be quite as detailed as we were
for reduce for reasons that will
become clear in just a moment.
This particular example, which
is in my ex14 folder in GitHub
repository, gets a list of
all the words in Shakespeare,
and then, in parallel,
will process that list
and end up with a single
set of all the unique words
in Shakespeare--
because, of course,
a set is not allowed duplicates.
So the way that this
will work is visualized,
at least partially, here in
the upper right-hand portion
of the slide.
We start out with all
the words of Shakespeare,
and then the parallel
spliterator will split that up
into the first half of the
words and the second half
of the words, and then
that will get further split
up into the first quarter of
the words, the second quarter
of the words, and so on.
Not going to take this all the
way down to the individual word
level.
Once we break it
down at that point,
though, we can then process
everything sequentially
in the fork-join pool.
Here's where things
get interesting.
When we run collect
here, will actually
end up mutating a result
container in order
to produce the
intermediate results.
And so what's going to happen
is each of the threads that
are running here
in the background
will start out with their own
intermediate mutable result
container, and they will go
ahead and essentially merge
the information from other
mutable result containers
together at each phase where
we're joining the results
together via collect.
So as you can see
in the diagram here,
we'll end up
merging the results,
say, from the first
quarter of the words
with the second
quarter the words,
and that will be
merged into a tree set.
So we'll end up with unique
words for the first half
of Shakespeare.
Same thing will happen
in the right-hand side.
You'll have the third
quarter of the words
and the fourth
quarter the words.
Those would be merged
together into a tree set
to find the unique words in
the second half of Shakespeare.
And then, finally, we'll
merge them together
in order to come up
with the final reduced
result, which is the
complete work of Shakespeare.
Every step along the way,
we're mutating the container
to accumulate the results
that's being produced.
There's also another way to
do this, which we'll also
talk about in further
detail later in the course,
and this is to use
something called
a concurrent collection--
concurrent collector.
And this is a little
different from
a non-concurrent collector.
The version we saw here,
which was using toCollection,
is a non-concurrent collector.
If we end up using a
concurrent collector,
all the words get
merged together
into one, single
result container.
Now, naturally that container
had darn well better
be thread-safe because multiple
threads in the fork-joint pool
will be merging things together
in there simultaneously.
So it has to be protected from
concurrent raise conditions
and other types of hazards.