So in our discussion
of DNS, we're
next going to cover some of
the challenges and issues that
can arise in making the
Domain Name System work.
The first challenge
is just reliability.
We've mentioned that the
DNS servers are replicated.
And the reason for this is
that if we query one of these,
the name service should be
available if at least one
of the replicas is up.
The other reason for this
would be for performance
so that queries could
get load balance
between different replicas.
So frequently, UDP is used
for performing these queries.
However, we'll get into
how UDP works in more
depth in some future lectures.
But UDP is not reliable.
So we would need to provide
some reliability mechanisms
on top of UDP if we're
going to use that.
The DNS specification
could support TCP, as well,
but it's not always implemented.
Other reliability
concerns would be
to try alternate servers
if there's a timeout.
So a common mechanism
to do that is
what's called exponential
backoff if you're
retrying the same server.
So you'd basically wait
exponentially increasing
amounts of time to try to
retry the same server and maybe
query alternatives if
a timeout's occurred.
The other issue
that could arise is
if we have the same identifier
for all the queries.
We don't really care which
server would respond.
So how can we insert
resource records into DNS?
How do we add things?
So let's say we created
a startup called FooBar--
just called FooBar, and we
want to register a domain name,
like foobar.com or something.
We'd get a block of
address space from an ISP.
So we'd be able to set
up, say, a web server.
Then we'd need to register that
domain name with a domain name
registrar.
So Network Solutions
is one example.
We'd provide the registrar
with the names and IP
addresses of the
authoritative name
server within the
organization, then
the registrar would insert
these resource record pairs
into the com top-level
domain name server.
So this is why the process
of registering a domain name
takes a little bit of time.
These updates need to occur.
So for example, though,
what this would look like--
say, foobar.com would be an
alias for dns1.foobar.com,
and then the
dns1.foobar.com would
correspond to a particular A
name record or this IP address.
OK, so that's what
we get inserted in
so that now when the com
top-level domain name
server gets a query
for foobar.com,
it knows how to respond to it.
So give it back that IP address.
Then in your
authoritative server,
you'd put in a couple records
for where the web server would
be, maybe a mail record
for what the mail
server is if you're going to
support mail on your own domain
name.
So this would go
into that host file
on your authoritative server--
so in this foobar.com
DNS1 server.
So there are a couple more
pieces to actually get
that set up to occur.
You'd need to provide the
reverse pointer bindings so
that we could map from the
IP address to the domain name
to go the opposite direction.
So then normally we'd do
that reversing process.
So a problem in
doing this is you
don't run that
domain name server.
So this just have to do with
you using a different block.
So in practice how that's
done for the reverse
lookups is the ISP
would run this for you.
But it's now more of a headache
to keep this information up
to date, and this is why the
reverse lookups don't always
work properly.
So some other challenge that
would arise are just security.
So what security issues could
come up in domain names?
Well, we have a lot of
degrees of freedom here.
So let's go through a
couple of possible examples.
So one initial
problem is as you're
sitting, say, in Starbucks
and browsing the web,
how does your laptop
find google.com?
Well, it's going to ask
the local domain name
server that would be
assigned probably with DHCP.
But that server is going to
be run by Starbucks, probably
a contractor in
reality, and they could
return anything they want.
So this is a wide opening for
a man-in-the-middle attack that
would forward your query
to Google, get the reply,
but then they could change
anything they want in either
direction.
So if it wasn't google.com
and it was your bank instead,
this could be a big problem.
So how do you know you're going
to get the correct data when
you do one of these queries?
You can't really.
If you're using HTTPS,
that would help,
but the contractor or whoever is
running that local domain name
server could still lie and
send you somewhere else.
But there are some security
extensions, this DNSSEC
protocol, that hopefully
would fix some of this.
But this still isn't
completely widely deployed.
A similar type of
security problem
is called cache poisoning.
Within this, if
there's a bad guy that
controls a name server for,
say, foobar.com, if you receive
a request to resolve
www.foobar.com,
you could reply back with
some additional information
and lie to the user
and instead direct
anything that's intended
for google.com to, say,
a particular server
that they control.
So one of the issues here--
so this would be that computer
run by the bad guy and not
the actual google.com server.
An issue that can
arise with this
and why this can be
difficult to detect
is that the evidence
of this attack
can disappear very quickly
based on that time-to-live field
length-- so say a
few seconds later.
So again, if it's
banking information,
let's say-- again,
not google.com,
but your bank-- you could
route someone's traffic
intended for their bank to
a server that they control.
So how would you get them to
look up a particular website
in the first place?
So any domain name
server could do that.
Any of them could lie
with those sections,
with the sort of faked
records to send traffic
to unintended destinations.
Well, there are some
things you could do.
You could send requests
to their mail server.
Then their mail server
would look up this address.
So that's one way you could
trick their name server
into requesting this invalid
domain name lookup that
would then poison the cache.
You could send them an
email with a link in there
to a particular URL.
If they clicked on it,
now you could have perhaps
poisoned the cache as well.
With a single
compromised name server,
we could also lie
about pointer records,
these reverse mappings--
so if we are in control
of managing these.
And you'll occasionally see
this happen where there's
a widespread DNS cache
poisoning attack,
and all the traffic
intended for something
gets routed somewhere else.
It's not too common, but
it does happen on occasion.
So let's look a little bit
more at cache poisoning.
So suppose the bad
guy's at Starbucks
and they can sniff for maybe
guess the identification
field of the local server
used in its next request.
Remember, the ID
field within DNS
corresponded to what
request and reply are
going to be linked together.
So if they ask the local
server for a recursive lookup
of google.com, they
could then locally
spoof the subsequent reply
from the correct domain name
server using that ID field if
they can figure out what it is.
Then, if the bogus reply
gets there sooner--
and it probably would because
it's on the local network--
the local server would
cache the bogus reply.
So now every future
Starbucks customer
would be served that
bogus answer out
of the local server's cache.
And if you did this, probably
you'd put in a large time
to live so that it would cause
this effect for a long time.
So whenever anybody browsed
to a particular website--
say, google.com-- instead
of it really going there,
it would be routed to some
server that's controlled
by that person, for example.
So let's just summarize what
we've seen about DNS now.
We talked about some of
the challenges just now.
But what is DNS,
just to remind you?
It's a distributed and
hierarchical database
that needs to get replicated
all over the world.
Indirection lets us use
these human-readable names
and also gives us the ability
to change the underlying IP
addresses.
It uses caching to
improve performance,
although that can lead
to some security issues.
And then we saw a little bit
of how the DNS protocol would
work using the dig utility.
The security issues that we've
discussed, like cache poisoning
and whatnot, arise
due to not having
any form of authentication.
So we don't know if
the reply is coming
from the correct or
a legitimate source.
We don't know if the
truth is being told.
There could be malicious
information inserted.
There could be bystanders
that spoof information
if they pick up what the
DNS message identifiers are.
And then playing with
the various caching
time-to-live lifetimes
adds power to these attacks
to either make them
go on for a long time
or to make them
disappear quickly so you
don't know that they occurred.
So that pretty much
summarizes how the domain name
system works.
And again, the key
reason we have this
is so that we don't have
to remember IP addresses,
and instead we can use
mnemonic, human-readable names,
like google.com
or vanderbilt.edu,
instead of having to
remember a long number
corresponding to those
organizations' computer systems
that we're trying
to interact with.