So now that we've introduced the
reason for why we have the DNS
system, let's talk a little
bit about how it works
and how we can work through
this mechanism of mapping
mnemonic names to IP addresses.
So just a few properties
of DNS to start
with-- so it is a hierarchical
namespace divided into zones,
then these zones are
distributed over a collection
of DNS servers.
And we'll show some
examples of this shortly
to clarify what those
zones would mean.
There's, then, a
hierarchy of DNS servers.
There are some root
DNS servers that
are hard wired so that other
servers can connect to them.
They're also top-level
domain, or TLD servers.
And then, finally, they're
also authoritative DNS servers.
So where does the
translation get performed?
So there can also
be local DNS servers
and, with resolver software
that would perform that,
look up to map a name
into an IP address.
So let's look a little bit
of how DNS would be organized
and what it would look like.
Roughly it would look like
this for some example domains.
So we would have a
root server, then
we would have top-level
domain servers.
The inside correspond
to like com, edu, .org.
There could be-- those
are generic domains.
There are many other domains,
such as country domains.
There may be other special
purpose domains, like arpa.
So then within these,
if we wanted to refer
to a particular website--
let's say, bar.edu-- it would
then be organized below this.
Then if we had further
subdomains or further prefixes
in front of that, maybe we have
one of these servers located
on the West Coast,
another on the East Coast,
and then within these we
could have some further break
down into this hierarchy.
So for example, to figure out
this name, the my.east.bar.edu,
so we would read
this from bottom
to top following this
street and similarly
for the other example.
So terminology wise, the com,
edu, org, et cetera servers,
these are called the top-level
domain servers, or TLDs.
And those domain
names, when they
are designated as
that top-level entry,
it would be the
top-level domain name.
So where is the DNS root server?
So one is located in Virginia.
But how do we make it scale?
So there really is not just one.
There are 13, roughly.
The number of these
can vary slightly,
but you can refer to the root
server .org website to see
where they're all located.
They're typically
labeled A through M.
And this will help scale
better if we geographically
distribute all these servers.
So for example,
on the East Coast,
there would be several from
organizations like Verisign.
One is run by NASA.
Then in other countries,
there would be other DNS root
servers.
So this would help us
scale a bit better.
However, now we need to
perform replication so
that all of these servers will
contain the same information,
so that if we look
up an IP address,
or rather we look up a domain
name to figure out what the IP
address is, no matter which
one of these root servers
we would query, we
need to get back
the same IP address that would
correspond to that domain name.
So the TLD, or top-level
domain servers,
again, these would host
the generic domains,
country-specific domains, other
special domains, like ARA.
These would typically be managed
professionally by companies.
For example, network solutions
maintain servers for com.
Educause maintain
servers for edu.
The last type of DNS server
that we haven't discussed yet
are authoritative DNS servers.
These would provide
public records
for hosts at a
particular organization.
These typically could
be private records.
So if you want to
refer to a printer
by a name and not part of sort
of the original designer's
intent-- so we may not
publish all of these around.
So this would be things
for organization servers
or other local things.
So these could be
maintained locally
or by a service provider.
So how does DNS work?
So you typically have
a local DNS server
located near end host so
that it would connect to it.
Then the local host
would be configured
with that local server
or would learn the server
through a mechanism
like DHCP, which we're
going to talk about later.
So we'd know where
the server is located
and what its IP address
is so we could talk to it.
The client application, then,
would extract the server name
from a URL and do
a get host named
to trigger the resolution
of a domain name.
Then a server application would
pull out the client IP address
from a socket or
from packets that
are incoming and could
translate that back into a name
if necessary.
So let's just see
a little example.
So let's suppose a
host cis.poly.edu wants
to get the IP address
for gaia.cs.umass.edu.
So this is the
requesting one, and this
is the host we want to figure
out the IP address for.
So the requesting host would
query the local DNS server--
so, say, at dns.poly.edu.
That could query
the root DNS server
to say, where is this located?
After responding back with what
top-level domain name server
to look the edu
information up at,
we could get a response
back from that.
Then after we figured out what
the authoritative DNS server is
for this particular host that
we're trying to figure out
the IP address of, we would
query this authoritative DNS
server at that organization.
It would then respond back
to the local DNS server
and then, finally,
send the information
to the original requesting host.
So that's roughly
how it would work.
So how did we know the
root server IP address?
Well, that's
hardcoded, essentially.
So there can be some
issues with that.
If it does change, if the IP
addresses of the root servers
change, there will typically
be some major announcements
like that.
So remember, they're
labeled A through M.
So if the D-root
changed its IP address,
there'd be
announcements about this
so that the correct
information could
get hard coded appropriately
so that these lookups would
proceed and work properly.
There are a couple
different kinds of queries.
What we saw an example
of, essentially,
was sort of a recursive query.
So we'd ask the server to
figure out the answer for it.
So this would look like that
request one and response eight.
So I'd say, the host would
say to its local DNS server,
find me this IP
address for this host.
An alternative mechanism
for how that could work
is through an
iterative query where
you could ask the local DNS
server who the next server is
to ask so that all of these
other requests response pairs
essentially would be iterative.
So this local DNS server
had asked the root DNS
server, who do I ask?
And then the TLD
servers would ask next,
and then it asks the
authoritative DNS server,
and then got back
with this response.
So sometimes we also need to go
the other direction from an IP
address to a
corresponding hostname.
So the addresses already
have a natural hierarchy
that's a little
bit similar looking
to the dots between
domain name portions.
But this quad notation has
the most significant hierarchy
element on the left, i.e.
the 12 appearing here, while
cnn.com has it on the right,
and that would be the
com top-level domain.
So an idea would be
to reverse the quads
and then start to
look up in DNS.
So we'll go over a little
bit of how that would work.
But basically the way this
would work under a particular
top-level domain, it would look
something like this where you
can see we've flipped--
we've just reversed this string
corresponding to the IP address
and then prefixed it
on this convention,
say, for something that's inside
of the arpa top-level domain.
And pictorially, that
reverse type of lookup
would be something
like this where,
if we were to read
now from the bottom,
we would see that encoding of
the zero is not shown here,
but the 56, then
the 34, then the 12,
then the in-address, then
arpa at the top-level domain.
So that will summarize a bit
about the high-level overview
of how DNS works, and then next
we're going to talk about a few
more details in terms of how
the DNS system overall operates
and some performance mechanisms
as well as some challenges that
arise.