So we'll continue
discussing DNS,
and next we'll discuss
some of the DNS protocol
and what some of the
data and commands,
the sends and receives,
requests/replies
in the DNS protocol, what
those are going to look like.
So what the information
in DNS is typically called
are called resource records.
And remember, as
we've introduced DNS,
we've described it as being
a distributed database that
stores information.
In this case, it's storing
these resource records.
So there's a format
of these consisting
of a name, a value, a type,
and a time to live, if any.
So there are several
types of DNS records.
Type A is kind of
the simplest type,
and that would
consist of a name that
is the hostname and a value
that's the IP address.
So this is the direct mapping
from a hostname into an IP
address.
Another type in these record
resource formats is a type NS.
Here the name is a
domain, so say foo.com,
and the value is a hostname
of an authoritative name
server for that domain.
For the reverse
lookups, the type PTR
would be the name represented
in that reverse quad notation
for doing reverse lookups,
and then the value
would be the
corresponding hostname
so that we could go from IP
address into that hostname.
Another type is
called a CNAME, which
stands for canonical name.
And what this corresponds
to is name mapping
to a canonical value.
So for example, the
address www.cs.mit.edu
really could correspond to the
canonical name eecsweb.mit.edu.
So this would let you give
some aliases essentially.
A final type, which we
won't talk too much about,
but is an MX type.
And the value for
this would be the name
of a mail server associated
with a particular domain name.
It could include some other
optional information as well.
So within the DNS
protocol, there
are two types of messages,
queries and replies,
and they both have
the same message
format which looks like this.
So the message header
consists of a variety
of pieces of information.
These are broken
into 16-bit portions.
The message header includes
a 16-bit number corresponding
to the query.
The reply to this query would
then use that same number
so you know you're
getting a response back,
basically just labeling or
identifying the query number,
if you will.
Flags that could
be set are options
like whether the type of
message is a query or a reply,
whether recursion is
desired or allowed,
or whether a reply is from an
authoritative source or not.
There would be other
fields including
the size of optional
header elements
that we won't talk
about in depth.
So what we're going to do
next to try to understand
a little bit more
about how DNS works is
we'll go through an interactive
lookup using the Unix program
called Dig.
What this lets you do is it
lets you query the DNS system,
and then it will dump the
field from the DNS responses,
so basically looking at
these DNS protocol messages.
So by default, it would
execute recursive queries
which you can disable
via this option just
to set that it's not
recursive so it's just going
to operate one step at a time.
So that's what we're going
to do through this quick
demonstration of this.
So let's suppose we want to look
up the IP address for cnn.com,
specifically, www.cnn.com.
And we're going to query
one of the root servers.
The root servers, again,
they're labeled A through M,
and you can access them through
this root-servers.net domain
name.
So if you run this
command, you'd
get back some responses, some
header information, of course.
In this case, you're
sending a query out.
The question that you're looking
for is, what is the A name?
Basically, what's the IP address
corresponding to cnn.com?
There's no answer section yet.
Then there's some
authoritative information
which is just
representing the various,
for this top-level domain,
com where you could look up
to figure out that answer.
So just going on
within the same query,
there would be additional
information corresponding
to what these top-level
domain name server names would
correspond to in IP addresses.
So we can see that, say--
let's look at the G one,
the G.GTLD-SERVERS.NET.
The A name record for that would
correspond to this IP address,
this 192.42.93.30.
There'd be some timing
information for this
and which server had replied.
If we go back and look,
we asked the root server
labeled A. That's the
server that had replied.
So after we figured out,
OK, I can go look up at A--
what this response
means is that I
can go ask now this root
server with the subdomain A
how to get to cnn.com.
Again, we didn't run this
in the recursive mode.
So now, if I ask one of the
top-level domain servers how
to get to cnn.com--
I'll just pick one of
them that had replied--
what we'll see now in some
of the responses for cnn.com,
we could access that with
this other domain name,
so this twdns-01.ns.aol.com.
So that'd be the domain
name server for cnn.com.
Then there'd be some additional
information encoding,
what are the actual IP
addresses corresponding
to those hostnames for
those domain name servers?
So moving along then, so
we'll do one more query.
If we now go query one of those
particular domain name servers,
we just picked one of them
arbitrarily out of the four
that came back with a
response and we ask it
what the IP address
for www.cnn.com
is, that was the question
that we asked that DNS server.
And we're asking it, what is
the IP address corresponding
to that domain name?
The response back that
we get and the answer
from the DNS system
is that www.cnn.com
is a CNAME or an
alias for cnn.com.
And then any of
these IP addresses
should work if you want
to access www.cnn.com.
So if you typed in your web
browser any of these addresses,
they should all
take you to cnn.com.
So there could be more
than one, as you can see.
And this could be for various
load balancing reasons
that we've mentioned
a little bit earlier,
having these geographically
distributed so that perhaps
a lookup or accessing that
website would be faster
in a certain region
of the world,
and you might be directed
to use a particular one
of those servers based
on that kind of criteria.
But this is how we would
have sort of manually
gone through that
process of getting
what IP address
corresponded to www.cnn.com.
So that's a little bit of an
overview of the DNS protocol,
the different types of resource
records like A name, CNAMEs,
and what some of the
information would
look like when the
queries and the DNS system
are actually occurring.