So the next topic
we'll discuss will
be how to assign easier
to remember names
so that we do not have to
remember IP addresses when we
want to talk to a particular
host or node on a network
or on the internet
in particular.
So the principle system
that enables us to do this
is called DNS, or the
Domain Name System.
What it allows us to
do is work with names
in place of the
numerical IP addresses
that the actual underlying
protocols, like the IP
protocol, depend upon.
It's also set up in
a hierarchical way
for scalability and a
variety of other reasons
so that we can reasonably
refer to these names and then
also what addresses and servers
would be corresponding to them.
It also incorporates caching
so that we have mappings
from names to or
from IP addresses.
And then we'll talk about some
of the inner workings of DNS
as well, such as DNS
resolvers and servers,
how queries in DNS and
the DNS protocol work.
There are iterative
and recursive versions.
We'll talk about
how caching works
and when timeouts would occur.
We'll talk a little bit about
how to do reverse lookups,
and we'll show
some demonstration
of using the dig
utility, which is
a Unix-based tool for querying
information within DNS.
So let's just quickly compare
host names versus IP addresses.
So host names will
be a mnemonic name
that we appreciate as humans,
whereas, as we've already
discussed IP
addresses at length,
those are numerical addresses
that are necessary for routers.
Hosts names will, of
course, be variable length
and will now use the full
alphabet of characters,
whereas IP addresses
were fixed length
and always corresponded under
the hood to some binary number.
The host names are
going to provide
little, if any, information
about a location,
whereas IP addresses were
defined in a hierarchical way,
and they were related
to the host location
so that we could perform
that routing process
to get information
where it needs to go.
So just some
examples, of course--
some hosts names,
like www.cnn.com.
Bbc.co.uk would provide a
little location information.
And these, of course,
are easier to remember
than the numerical quantities
in the IP addresses below.
So how do we separate the
naming from the addressing?
And why do we do this?
Well, of course, names
are easier to remember.
The other reason is that
underneath the addresses
could change.
Perhaps we change
the server that's
hosting the website
cnn.com or perhaps we
change a service provider.
The other thing is a
name could actually
map to multiple IP addresses.
Perhaps for load balancing
or scalability reasons
we have multiple
replicas of a website--
so handling load balancing,
reducing latency,
if perhaps we put a
server hosting cnn.com,
say, in different
countries so that there
is always one close by
to people likely to try
to access that server.
We could also do things
like tailor the content
based on the requester's
location or identity.
And we could have multiple
names for the same address
within this so that
we could have aliases.
And there may be good
reasons to do that.
So "www," if that's prefixed
in a domain name, typically
would correspond
to a web server.
But if you just access cnn.com,
that probably also works
and gets directed to the web
server, whereas cnn.com might--
it doesn't have to direct
to that web server.
So how does this work roughly?
How does this mapping between
names and addresses work?
So originally this was
done in a per-host file
working with a flat namespace.
Typically under Unix,
it'd be in /etc/hosts,
and then an organization, one
of the first organizations
on the internet and the
web, SRI in Menlo Park,
would keep a master copy.
So then others would need to
download this file regularly.
But this isn't going to scale.
If there are a lot of lookups
and if one organization was
keeping track of this, it
could overload that server,
and it would lead to a
single point of failure.
So this will motivate
how DNS works
and why we need a distributed
and hierarchical collection
of servers so that
this would scale up.