So next we'll
discuss a mechanism
within DNS that helps
it perform better
because, as we saw with our
example of a lookup in the DNS
system to find the IP address
corresponding to a hostname,
we saw that it requires
quite a few queries.
So it'd be better if
we could integrate
in some kind of a
caching mechanism
to reduce all of those lookups.
So that's what DNS caching does.
And the reason, again, is that
performing all those queries
can take time.
And all of this
time is before any
of the actual communication
we actually care about
takes place.
So for example, if
it took one second
before a web page would
start to load every time,
it'd probably be
fairly annoying.
So if we do use caching, we can
greatly reduce the overhead.
Part of the reason that we
can take advantage of this
is that those top-level
domain servers are very rarely
going to change.
So popular sites like CNN.com
are going to be visited a lot,
so then the local DNS server
can have that information cached
so it doesn't have to go
through all of those queries
to figure out what the IP
address is for CNN.com.
So roughly, how
that caching process
would work in DNS is the
DNS servers would cache
the responses to the queries
so that, the next time a lookup
would occur, it doesn't have to
go through that whole process
of sending and
receiving messages
all the way up to the
top-level domain name server
and the root DNS servers.
It would just know the answer
of what the IP address is.
This response would
also include a time
to live field so that we know
how long before the DNS server
is forced to go look up
that IP address again.
So after that time
would expire, the server
would delete that cached entry.
So there's another
concept in caching
that can also help improve
performance and particularly
usability.
That's called negative
caching, and this
would be remembering
things that did not work.
So for example, if you
accidentally misspell a domain
name-- like if you put two M's
or mistype CNN and put three
N's--
the only way that your
computer figures out
or that the lookup figures out
that these are probably not
valid domain names is by going
through that whole DNS querying
process.
So you'd send all those
messages to figure out, oh, this
wasn't a valid domain name.
And then you look
at the domain name
and you see you mistyped it.
Right?
Of course, there
could be other things
like someone expecting some
misspellings of common names
has registered that
domain that's actually
a spam site of some form.
So these things could
take a long time
to fail the first time
because all of those lookups
need to occur, and you need
to get that response back
from an authoritative
DNS server in the end
that there's no IP address
corresponding to that name.
So it'd good to
remember things that
don't work so that the
failure would take less
time the next time and
not all of those messages
would need to be sent to figure
out that that server didn't
exist at all.
Unfortunately, this is
an optional process,
and right now, it's really
not widely-implemented.
But overall, this
caching process,
we talked about, primarily,
the positive caching process,
that we would save the IP
addresses corresponding
to commonly looked
up domain names so
that the next lookup isn't
going to take nearly as long.