So next we'll discuss the
Address Resolution Protocol,
which is used to come up with
a mapping between MAC addresses
and IP addresses.
So let's first give a little
bit of an overview of how
this process works.
So recall that we have
32-bit IP addresses.
This is used for
network layer services.
So for IP type of
services, we're
doing forwarding of information
through the network.
The MAC address--
or LAN, physical,
or ethernet address would
be some other common terms
for this--
this would be used locally
to get access to an interface
and to send that
information that's
necessary to be sent to another
interface in the same network.
So very low level sort of
link layer type of an address,
so we'll see some more details.
So the 48-bit MAC address is
put into the network interface
card's read-only memory,
but sometimes its software's
settable, so you may know how
to change this in a higher level
operating system.
So what would this look
like with these LAN or MAC
addresses?
So every computer
on the network would
be associated with a MAC
address, every interface card.
And then if we want to send
information between hosts,
we use this MAC address.
This is what the adapters
actually understand.
They don't understand
IP addresses.
So how MAC addresses are
assigned or allocated
is administered by IEEE.
When someone wants to produce
network interface cards,
they'd buy a portion of
the MAC address space
to try to ensure uniqueness,
although, occasionally, there
can be duplicate
MAC addresses and it
can cause all sorts of
interesting network problems.
But analogously, you can
think of the MAC address
sort of like a social
security number
and the IP address sort
of like a postal address.
The MAC addresses are flat,
which enables portability
so you can move between
different networks,
whereas the IP address
space was hierarchical
and it's not really portable.
It depends on what IP subnet
the node is attached to.
So what the address resolution
or ARP protocol does
is it would determine an
interface's MAC address knowing
its IP address.
So this is basically
how it operates.
So I have all these hosts.
They have IP addresses and MAC
addresses assigned to them.
So this is done through the
usage of a table called the ARP
table.
For this, each IP node, so a
host or router on the network
would have this table,
and this would only
be the local network.
So we don't do this
over the internet.
The IP and MAC address
mappings for some land nodes
would basically appear like
IP address, MAC address,
and a time to live.
So this would be the time after
which the address mapping would
get forgotten, typically
set to about 20 minutes.
So let's go over some
of the usage of the ARP
protocol on the same LAN.
So suppose A wants
to send information
to B. B's MAC address
is not in A's ARP table.
So what would occur is A would
broadcast an ARP query packet
containing B's IP address.
It would send it out
to the broadcast MAC
address, which is all Fs.
All the nodes on the LAN
would receive that query.
B would receive that
ARP packet as well,
and it would reply to
A with B's MAC address.
So that would be sent
to A's MAC address
because A had attached its
MAC address in that broadcast
query.
A would then cache the IP to MAC
address pair in its ARP table
until that information
expired or became old.
So ARP is plug-and-play, so the
nodes do create their own ARP
tables without intervention
from the network administrator.
So let's walk through an
example of how this would work.
So let's suppose we want
to send information from A
to B through router R. And
we're going to focus on all the
addressing aspects here, both
the IP addressing and the MAC
addressing portions.
So let's assume that A knows
B's IP address already.
Let's also assume that A knows
the IP address of the first hop
router, which could have been
determined, say, with DHCP.
Assume A also knows
R's MAC address,
which it could have already
discovered through that ARP
process that we just discussed.
So what would happen is A
would create a message or an IP
datagram with its source
A and its destination B
using those IP addresses.
So we have the IP address for
A is the source IP address.
The IP address for B is
the destination IP address.
Then what would happen is it
would create a link-layer frame
with R's MAC address.
That's the router we
need to route through
as the destination address.
And then the frame would contain
the A to B IP layer message.
So what we can see
here is the source
MAC address has been
set to A's MAC address.
The destination MAC
address has been
set to the incoming
link of router R,
so we can see this
E6 starting here.
So that frame would
get sent from A to R
over this lower-layer protocol,
the link and physical layer
protocols.
When that's received
by the router,
it would remove the datagram.
It would see that the
information was intended
for it because its destination
MAC address had been set to it.
Then it would pass this
information up to the IP layer.
We'd see the destination
address as 22 repeated.
We know that needs to be routed
out through this outgoing link
after we've constructed
a routing table.
R would then forward this
datagram or this message
with the IP source
as A's, so leaving
the IP message
basically the same
and leaving the destination
as B's IP address.
R would then prefix
in front of that--
the link-layer frame information
with B's MAC addresses
as the destination address--
so that this frame would now
contain the A to B datagram.
So what we can see is
that the source address
is this incoming from
the perspective of B.
It's this interface on
the router's MAC address.
And the destination MAC address
is the MAC address of B.
So in this way, the
information could
get sent over to B from A. And
the addressing all the way down
to the link-layer would
have been accommodated.
B would then strip off the
link-layer header information
and pull out the IP
layer information.
So that summarizes the
way that ARP works.
And again, what this
would do is come up
with the mapping between IP
addresses and MAC address
pairs.
It does this in the ARP table.
When a packet needs to be sent,
it would consult the ARP table
so that it could look up
the actual MAC address
of the destination.
And then it would
encapsulate it.
So this, again,
just would be put
in front of the packet
header of the IP header,
say, for the link-layer header.
So if we didn't have the
IP address in the table,
what would occur is the
sender would request,
who has that IP address?
The receiver would respond
back, and then the sender
would cache that
result. So there
are more details for
this link-layer protocol,
but it's necessary to be
able to connect things up
and to bootstrap
the IP connectivity.