The next topic we'll discuss
is how we assign IP addresses.
So how do we first
come up with an IP
address for a
particular interface--
so for a particular computer.
So there are a few
mechanisms for this.
Typically, it's done through
a bootstrapping or startup
process.
There are two mechanisms We'll.
Discuss that
accomplish this one is
called DHCP, which
a node would use
to learn its own
configuration parameters.
There is another
process to learn
the link-layer addresses
of other nodes, which
is done with ARP.
So I'll first talk
primarily about DHCP.
So for example,
what IP address--
if we've added a new host to
a network, what IP address
should that host use?
What DNS server should it use?
How can it disambiguate
which destinations
are local versus on
some external network?
How could we address to those
destinations if they are local?
And then how do we send packets
out to a remote destination--
typically, through
some gateway router.
So those are the problems
we're going to try to address.
So we'd prefer not to just
encode all of this information
manually.
That would be one solution,
but it will be pretty brittle,
and it wouldn't scale well.
So DHCP stands for the Dynamic
Host Configuration Protocol.
And with this,
each end host would
learn how to send packets.
So basically it would learn
IP addresses, DNS servers,
a gateway node to
send information out
through to other networks
and what addresses are local.
In the Address Resolution
Protocol, or ARP,
this is for local destinations.
This would discover the
mapping between IP addresses
that are used at the network
layer and Mac addresses, which
are used at the link layer--
so the lower level addressing.
So for both protocols,
there are a few key ideas.
The first is broadcasting.
So if you don't know something,
shout to get the answer.
The broadcast query would
be sent to all hosts
in the local area network--
so in the LAN that
you're connected to.
And this is what you do if
you don't know how to identify
the correct other host.
Caching will also be
incorporated in these protocols
to remember past
information for a while--
so store what you learned
to reduce overhead
and having to send too many
requests for information--
and also to store your
own address and other host
addresses.
So this caching process is
also a form of soft state.
So you'd eventually
forget the past.
So you'd associate some time
to live with that information
and then either refresh
or discard information
if it times out.
And this is important
for robustness in case
of unpredictable changes.
So what's a Mac address
versus an IP address?
So the Mac address
is something that's
hard coded, whereas
the IP address is
something that would be
configured or learned
dynamically.
So you can sort of think of
a Mac address like a Social
Security number and an IP
address like a postal mailing
address number.
So even if you
move, probably you
keep the same Social
Security number.
But you might wind up
with a new postal address.
Mac addresses are a flat
namespace-- so 48 bits.
So they'll typically
be written in hex
and look something like this.
They'd be portable, and
they could stay the same
as the host would move around.
And this is what's
used at the link layer
to get packets between
interfaces on the network.
In contrast, as
we've already seen,
IP addresses are a hierarchical
namespace using 32 bits--
so in that dotted quad notation.
These wouldn't
necessarily be portable.
It would depend on where
the host is attached.
But this is what's used
for doing the network
layer, the
internel-level routing,
to figure out
destination IP subnets.
So the bootstrap
problem is that when
a host gets connected to
a network or turns on,
it doesn't have
an IP address yet.
So it doesn't know
what source address
to use to send information
out using the IP protocol.
It also doesn't know who
to ask for an IP address.
So what it will do at first
to be able to figure out
what destination
addresses would make sense
and what source address
it's been assigned
is it would send out a
broadcast to discover
a server that can help.
So it broadcasts out a
server discovery message
to this special Mac address.
Then the server, or possibly
servers, running, say, DHCP,
would respond back
offering an address.
So the response
from the DHCP server
would consist of an offer.
This would have
configuration parameters,
like the proposed IP address,
mask information, a gateway
router IP address, DNS
server, IPs, et cetera.
It would also
include a lease time,
which would be the duration
for which that IP address would
remain valid.
Several servers could respond.
There might be multiple DHCP
servers on the same broadcast
network.
They could each respond.
But you should probably
just pick one of them.
Otherwise, your IP address
wouldn't be unique.
The client would send a request
echoing the parameters back
to accept an offer,
and the DHCP server
would respond with
an acknowledgment.
And the other DHCP servers,
if there are multiple offers,
they would see that
they weren't chosen.
So roughly, this is what
a run of the protocol
would look like.
DHCP discover gets sent
out through the broadcast
mechanism-- so to all
computers or all things
attached to the network.
It would offer an IP address
gateway information, et cetera,
to the client.
The client could broadcast
back sending a request that,
OK, I'll take that, and
then the DHCP server
would acknowledge back.
So why do we
incorporate a lease time
so that information
can be forgotten?
So the client could request
release of the IP address
to get a new IP
address or this could
occur if the client shuts down.
However, the client might
not release the address.
So suppose the computer crashes.
If you don't release the
address and have a timeout,
then that address would
have been allocated forever,
and we want to
avoid that scenario.
So there can be some performance
trade-offs with these lease
times.
So if it's a short
lease time, the address
that's been allocated
would time out quickly.
But if it's long, you
would avoid this overhead
of frequent renewals.
But it would
increase, potentially,
the chance of running
out of IP addresses.
So now the host has information,
like, what the IP address is
that it's been assigned,
what the network mask is-- so
what the subnet information
is-- what a gateway is,
and what DNS servers are.
So now it could send out
packets to other IP addresses.
But how can we use the local
network to accomplish this?
So how would a node
figure out if it's
sending something
locally versus remotely?
So there's two cases for this.
If the destination's
on the local network,
you can go ahead and
address it directly.
If it's not, then you
need to figure out
where to send it through, which
typically would be the gateway
router.
So if it's on the
local network, you
can determine that by comparing
the mask that's been assigned.
So if you take the
destination address
and conjunct it with
the mask and then
if you get back the same value
as when the hosts own addresses
mask, then you know it's local.
So for example, if this host
wanted to send something
to this host and it
took the mask of this,
it might get back
something like 1.2.3,
and it would know that,
OK, the dot seven is also
on the same local network.
So if it's remote,
though, we'd need
to look up the first hop
on the local routing table.
So that would be whatever
gateway had been assigned.
So then we would
do the same thing
for the local case
for this gateway
rather than the ultimate
destination IP address.
For the local case,
we'd need to figure out
the destination's Mac address.
And the reason
that we would need
to do that is because
sending packets
over a link, the network
interface cards only
understand Mac addresses.
So that destination
IP address needs
to get translated
into a Mac address.
And what would occur
is the IP packet
would get encapsulated
inside of a link level frame.
So basically we would
prefix in front of it
the link-level information, as
we've seen some other earlier
examples of.