So next, we'll discuss a
little bit of the detail
and how the DHCP protocol
works to dynamically assign
IP addresses.
So the problem we're solving
is how do we get an IP address
when we don't have one.
So how would a host get one?
So it could be hard-coded
by a system administrator.
There are ways to do this.
You can manually set
the IP of your computer
in windows Unix and
other operating systems.
However, that's pretty brittle
if you put in the wrong value,
if things change.
So what's commonly
used is called
DHCP which would
dynamically find an IP
address from a server.
So the goal of the
DHCP protocol is
to allow the hosts
to dynamically
find an IP address
from the network server
when it joins the network.
So it could renew this
when a lease expires.
So essentially a time to live
off how long that address
is valid.
You could then reuse
addresses, support
for mobile users who
want to join the network
and then leave perhaps.
So basically, we're going to
walk through how DHCP works.
This is just a brief
overview of it.
The host could broadcast
DHCP discover message.
The DHCP server would respond
with an offer message.
The host would
request an IP address.
And the DHCP server would
respond with an acknowledgment.
So let's look at this
kind of scenario.
Let's suppose we have a
network setup in this way.
We have a few subnet setup.
There's a DHCP server connected
on one of the subnets.
And we have a laptop
joining the network,
and now it needs an IP address
so that it can communicate
with the local network
as well as beyond, say,
on the internet.
So the DHCP server, as the
arriving client gets connected,
it realizes it doesn't
have an IP address,
so it sends out a broadcast.
Is there a DHCP
server available?
It would have included
some information
within that discovery about what
it may think some of the source
address should be.
So the source address
of 0.0.0.0, this
would effectively be a
broadcast type of address,
likewise that destination
address of 255 repeated
is indicating a broadcast.
So the DHCP server
would receive that.
It would interpret
it and say, OK.
I'm a DHCP server.
And it would send a message
back encoded with its IP back
to everyone.
So again, it
broadcasts because it
doesn't know how to address
that client because that client
doesn't have an IP address.
So then the arriving
client would say, OK.
I'll take an IP address.
It again does this
through a broadcast,
because it still doesn't have
an IP address assigned yet.
Then the DHCP server
would respond back
with an acknowledgment
and say, OK.
You've got that
particular IP address.
And now it would have
assigned an IP address,
but this would have come through
this broadcast from the DHCP
server because the
arriving client, up
until this particular
point in this time flow,
it didn't have an
IP address assigned.
So DHCP can do a bit more than
just assigning IP addresses.
It can return more than
just that allocated
address on the subnet.
It typically would
provide a gateway, names,
and addresses of a
DNS server as well
as what the network
mask would be.
So indicating the network versus
the host portions of the IP
address.
So let's look at
another DHCP example.
So let's suppose we
connect this laptop.
It needs an IP address
of the first-hop router.
And oftentimes, that first-hop
router in your home network
would have a DHCP
server built in.
So it would build
up this request.
It would encapsulate this, say
starting at DHCP relies on UDP.
So it would be that
transport layer message
then an encapsulated
into an IP message
using the broadcast address
then sent down on the link layer
saying ethernet if it's
physically plugged in.
That ethernet frame would
get broadcasted to everyone
on the LAN, sort of like how
in [INAUDIBLE] protocol worked.
This would get received by this
router running the DHCP server.
It would then get decoded,
see its DHCP information
so that demuxing process would
strip off all that header
information until it gets
down to the relevant DHCP
information.
The DHCP server would then
formulate an acknowledgment
containing the client's
IP address, the IP
address of the first-hop router,
this node itself, the name
and IP address of a DNS server.
So then encapsulate
that back down
to the link layer of course and
send it over to the Mac address
corresponding to
that particular node.
So their client would now know
its IP address and the name
and address of the DNS server
as well as the first-hop gateway
or router IP address.
So it's just look
at a little bit
of a log recorded from Wireshark
on a home LAN for this process.
So this would be the
request from the client
and this would be the
reply from the DNS server
or from the DHCP server.
So initially, the
request, as we can see--
maybe a little bit small--
but the client IP address
is just assigned as all zeros,
but we do see the Mac address
encoded for the client there.
Right so then the reply
from the DHCP server
would have the IP
address encoded in it.
All right.
So the IP that's been assigned.
The gateway address and some of
these other components like DNS
servers That we've
also discussed.
By sending out this
broadcast information,
getting this reply from a
DHCP server on the network,
this is how this new
node joining the network
would have been
assigned its IP address.